let's start with you john if that's okay
sure how you see yourself
and how you see assange and what both of
your cases reveal about the treatment of
whistleblowers
oh sure and also can you set up your
story in case people don't know about it
certainly uh and and before the hour's
over
remind me to say something about the
effect of calls
to members of congress i spent years on
capitol hill
and they really do have an effect oh
well we can all do that i'm not even
kidding we can do that
now okay yeah listen i worked on the
house side and the senate side the
senate's a little tougher but in the
house
you know sometimes they jump too with
just
one phone call or one letter they're
very responsive to constituents
on the house side so by all means email
call do whatever is easiest for you
because they'll they'll respond and
react to it
on the senate side they have usually
interns or young staff members
who just collate all the calls and the
emails coming in so if there
is a number of communications
coming in on an issue that will make its
way to the senator
so this is not a waste of time
this actually works i would encourage
everybody to call their
their members okay we have both numbers
we have both numbers the only difference
is there was something different if john
if you can remind me
there was something different about the
thing with the representatives that
obviously you have to know who it is and
there
so but we have all the numbers we have
everything there and you can call
202 22431
which is the capitol hill operator and
if you don't know
your member the operator
is trained to identify who that is and
refer your call to the right office
can you say that number again i'm just
going to put it in there wait it's on
our phone script you see it on our
screen
it's at the top of the script yeah but i
just want to put it in the chat so
they oh okay okay so 202 you bet it's
uh 2 2 4 three one two one
great okay now we have it there okay
excellent so uh my name is john kiriakou
i'm a former cia officer
and uh to make a very long story very
short
i uh blew the whistle on the cia's
torture program in 2007
i was prosecuted by the obama
administration in 2012
and facing 45 years in prison i ended up
taking a deal that sent me to
a federal prison uh for 23 months
where where i had the fabulous
support of code pink and my friend kevin
gestala came to visit me a number of
times
uh julian assange has always been
a beacon of transparency
and honestly i can't think of very many
things that are more important
than transparency in government uh
one of the things that i like to repeat
almost as a mantra
because people just don't get it for
some reason is that julian assange is a
journalist
and even more than a journalist he's a
publisher
and what i don't understand is why the
mainstream media is not lining up behind
him
because it's clear to the rest of us
that if julian is extradited to the
united states and he's prosecuted
every one of these national security
journalists
at the washington post in the new york
times and the wall street journal etc
they're next and then who's going to go
to bat for them
so this is a not me not me not if they
don't go to bed for julian no no
seriously
i'm gonna i'm gonna snitch on them i'm
gonna yeah seriously my dress is out i'm
just kidding
this has been going on for so long for
so many years that everybody who needs
to
form an opinion and come down on one
side of the issue or the other
has had the time and the opportunity to
do that
so the fight's not over of course uh the
judge
while taking swipe after swipe at julian
in her decision
came down on the right side of it by uh
declining to
extradite uh kevin's an expert on this
issue yeah and you know there was a
there's precedent in the uk both in the
uk and in the european court of human
rights
to not extradite prisoners to the united
states because of the way that solitary
confinement is used as a punishment here
people lose their minds in solitary
confinement in the united states
you know it was newsworthy yesterday
when the state of new york announced
that they would abide by united nations
recommendations in not keeping people in
solitary for more than
15 consecutive days well that's great
but we're the only industrialized
country that
doesn't abide by that right
we've we've had people and medea and i
have talked about this
in other venues we we've had people in
the united states in solitary
confinement with literally no
human contact for as long as 44
years now can you imagine not seeing or
speaking with another human
being for 44 years and then eventually
you're released from prison and you're
expected to live a normal life and be a
law-abiding citizen
it's outrageous but anyway
the issue here is is julian and i feel
like we're close but we're not
quite there yet and that's why we need
to keep up the pressure especially on
our elected officials and the justice
department as you're doing today
to make this thing go away it's amazing
to me that here in washington where
people are supposed to be so smart right
we're all the smartest people in america
here in washington
that they don't realize that this is a
pandora's box
and once that lid is opened and
everything comes out
you can't put it back in this is if
julian is extradited to the united
states
this is going to change the way the
constitution is interpreted
forever yeah forever it's a direct
assault on our first amendment rights
and so we're a little bit ahead of
things now
for the first time in many many years we
have to finish it off and win
it yeah and do you have any advice from
your
um personal story about what gets people
interested or how people can be made
aware
of what's happening or realizing that
this is an important story thanks for
that question katie
i do i feel like when you're able to
personalize things
people sit up and take notice you know
sometimes
a story is so outrageous that
people can't help but to be interested
they can't help but to then offer their
support
i feel like this is one of those those
cases
because you know over the course of the
last
what 12 years from the beginning of the
obama administration
the definition of espionage has changed
in my view it's changed dramatically
it's been simplified which is very very
dangerous
the the courts now the federal courts in
the united states um
they define espionage as providing
national defense information to any
person not entitled to receive it
period now if you look at the espionage
act it goes for you know 30 pages
but that's the definition that's used in
court
well that could be you know you could
arrest a thousand people every day
for laying in bed before you go to sleep
and mentioning to your wife something
that you did
at work that day well you guess what
that's national defense information
so if a president doesn't like
what's been reported in the washington
post or in the new york times
with a president with a precedent of
julian assange having been
arrested and prosecuted then
again what's to keep those reporters
from being prosecuted
and as soon as those reporters are
prosecuted
that ends constitutional protections for
the rest of us
so i think that we need to personalize
this we need to explain to people
in plain english why it's so
important and why this isn't a fight
that's sort of off in the distance
between
um a transparency group and the american
government
this is a fight that impacts every
single one of us
that that's my guess number one yeah is
is personalizing it number two and i'll
say it again
especially on the house side
those members of congress jump when
their constituents
write letters because most people don't
write letters or
in today's situation emails
but um most people don't take the five
minutes
to write and express an opinion so when
they get
an email or 10 or 100 on an issue
they react to it i can't tell you how
many times
we would get a letter saying you know
please co-sponsor
hr12345 just because i'm asking you to
and we would read it and say well what
the heck is hr one two three four five
okay yeah well if this constituent wants
it sure we'll
co-sponsor that and we would we'd
co-sponsor it
now on the senate side when i was
working for john kerry in the senate
foreign relations committee
one call is not going to make a
difference but 10 or 20 calls are going
to make a difference
at the very least it's going to push
the issue onto his agenda and so
imagine what a hundred calls could do
or 500 calls i mean that's real activism
right there
i just want to say that for um anybody
who it doesn't necessarily feel
comfortable leaving a message
but we have a longer form of our script
that is also available that you also you
could use the script as an email as well
so if people do feel comfortable sending
an email but they don't really feel
comfortable calling please feel free to
copy and paste
thanks for watching if you want to
support our mission to transform
politics into service
please like this video subscribe follow
us on social media
and consider joining our patreon where
you'll get early access to our
interviews
as well as other exclusive content links
are in the description
peace out